Guide to the Andrews Memorial Bookplate Collection of Irene D. Andrews Pace (Japanese Bookplates)
Yale University Arts Library
Andrews Memorial Bookplate Collection of Irene D. Andrews Pace (Japanese Bookplates)
1910-1961
BKP 7
Yale University Arts Library
0.42
(1 box)
The collection consists of bookplates by Japanese artists, for Japanese patrons, or both. Individual and institutional patrons are represented.
Andrews, Irene Dwen, 1892-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Irene D. Andrews Pace, 1963, in memory of Dr. Edmund Andrews (Yale 1913) and his father, Dr. E. Wyllys Andrews.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Born Irene Greene Dwen, Mrs. Pace (1892-1962) was an avid bookplate collector from the early 1920s until 1962. In addition to over 150,000 plates in her collection, she also maintained a reference library related to bookplates, as well as heraldry and biographical research. Pace commissioned several hundred bookplates for herself. In 1936, she published Owners of Books: The Dissipations of a Collector.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of bookplates by Japanese artists, for Japanese patrons, or both. Individual and institutional patrons are represented.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Bookplates – Individuals. II. Bookplates – Institutions. III. Bookplates – Unidentified. IV. Ephemera.
Bookplates, Japanese; Bookplates
- Bookplates – Individuals, Series I
  Arrangement
  This series includes bookplates arranged by patron or artist. Some items have the patron's name but are missing the bookplate.
  - Andrews – Casares, 1914-1960 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    In Folder 1, the Atgioi bookplate is also identified as Pouvourille. One of the Haagen Bartram-Jensen bookplates is identified by the artist Shimozawa.
  - Cardenosa – De Olaneta, 1960 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dick – Estiarte, 1935-1960 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fogedgard – Hirose, 1935-1959 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - E. Hirose, 1935 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - I. Hirose – Kawanishi, 1938-1960 undated; 11 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Keitaro – Kozuka, 1932-1961 undated; 11 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Kudernatsch – Maekawa, 1938-1960 undated; 12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mayerova – Ohata, 1936-1960 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ogilvie – Perrottet, 1934-1959 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Rhebergen – Seimiya, 1951-1960 undated; 11 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Seki – Takei, 1934-1961 undated; 11 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Tanaka – B. Wille-Nielsen, 1910-1960 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - M. Wille-Nielsen – Yuste, 1950-1960 undated; 12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bookplates identified by artist-only: Hata – Takii, 1960-1961 undated; 6 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Bookplates – Institutions, Series II
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Nenching University – Nippon Association Ex Libris, undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Bookplates – Unidentified, Series III
  - Assortment of unidentified bookplates, undated; 12 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Assortment of unidentified bookplates, undated; 12 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series IV: Ephemera
  This series includes a book entitled, Bookplates of Japan, edited by Shozo Saito, Meiji-Shobo (Tokyo, 1941). The book was a limited edition of 350 copies, of which 50 were distributed by the publisher as gifts and 300 were made available for sale. The Arts Library Special Collections department has three different copies of the book. Bookplate #37 is missing from the edition included here.
  - Greeting Cards: Hirose – Richard, 1953 undated; 4 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bookplates of Three Illustrious Family of Nippon by Shoji Kozuka, Crest Chart, prints, 1936 undated; 5 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bookplates in Japan: 1-10, 1941; 10 items (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bookplates in Japan: 11-20, 1941; 10 items (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bookplates in Japan: 21-30, 1941; 10 items (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bookplates in Japan: 31-40, 1941; 10 items (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bookplates in Japan: 41-50, 1941; 10 items (Box 1, Folder 25)